Finding Aid for William Charles Parkinson Papers, 1928-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Charles Parkinson Papers 1950-1997, 1950-1980
Parkinson, William Charles, 1918-
5.25 linear feet
8733 Aa 2
Professor of physics at the University of Michigan (1947-1988); director of the cyclotron laboratory, 1962-1977; inventor of method and apparatus for measuring the velocity of a projectile and of an automatic timing and sequence-indicating system used in swimming. Series in the collection relate to cyclotron laboratory and research; department of physics activities, including history; professional organizations; swimming judging and timing system; University of Michigan committee assignments; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by William C. Parkinson (Donor No. 7962 ) in July 1991.A second accession received on May 1, 2012.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William C. Parkinson was born February 11, 1918 in Jarvis, Ontario. He received his BSE (1940), Master's (1941), and Ph.D. (1948), all in physics, from the University of Michigan. His professional association with the University of Michigan began in 1936 when he became a research assistant. In 1942, he left Ann Arbor to become a physicist at the Applied Physics Lab at Johns Hopkins University. He also worked at Johns Hopkins' Office of Science Research and Development in 1943-44. Parkinson returned to the University of Michigan in 1946 as a research fellow. In 1947 he joined the faculty as an instructor and was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1948 then to professor in 1958. From 1962 to 1977, Parkinson also was the director of the cyclotron laboratory on the Ann Arbor campus.
The cyclotron was an "atom-smasher" that accelerated particles to relatively high energy, and was a principal instrument for research in nuclear structure physics. The University of Michigan cyclotron program dates back to 1935 when what was then the largest cyclotron in the world was constructed. The facility was remodeled and updated in 1950 with help from the UM Phoenix Project. In 1960, a grant from the Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) as well as $1.1 million from the Michigan State Legislature provided for the construction of the University-owned building to house both the original 42-inch cyclotron and a new 83-inch cyclotron.
Parkinson has had four patents issued which are associated with various research projects. These include a method and apparatus for measuring the velocity of a projectile (1961), method and apparatus for remotely controlling an airborne vehicle (1950), and two versions of an automatic timing and sequence-indicating system used in swimming (1966, 1967).
His swim judging and timing system came from his own love of the sport and his experiences as a timer at Michigan swimming meets. He felt that the human factor in timing and judging led to too many disputes and uncertainties. His impressions were borne out when there was a controversial decision in the outcome of the 100-meter men's freestyle race in the 1960 Olympics. A more universal need for an accurate system led to more interest in the system Parkinson had been working on since 1958 with Michigan swim coach Gus Stager. Parkinson's system used two electrical circuits and contact plates. The timing circuit, started by the sharp report of the starting gun, was stopped by the first contact plate being touched. The judging circuit gave the order or sequence of finish. "Touch pads" were lowered into the pool at the last lap for swimmers to make contact with and record the times. The system effectively eliminated the human link, except for the placing of the contact pads, and was unaffected by waves and splash.
Parkinson served on various professional and university committees during his lifetime, which highlight his own varied professional and personal interests. He was named a Fulbright Scholar (1952-53) and served as a consultant for Oak Ridge National Lab (1955-1960), Los Alamos National Lab (1958-60), and Argonne National Lab (1959-60). His membership on various university committees ranged from the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics to Rackham Divisional Board policies and the Biophysics Research Division Executive Committee.
Parkinson retired on May 31, 1988, was appointed Professor Emeritus, and was reappointed to active status for Fall 1989. Parkinson passed away on March 19, 2012.
The William C. Parkinson Papers consist of 5.25 linear feet of documents relating to the professional career of physics professor William C. Parkinson, spanning years 1950 through 1990 with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 1980. The papers were received in two major accession in July 1991 and May 2012.
The first accession was broken into five series: Cyclotron, Physics Department, Professional Organizations, Swimming Judging and Timing System, and University Committees. There is also a folder entitled "Biographical/Historical Information" at the beginning of the collection which includes a 1974 vita and a publication on the cyclotron laboratory of which Parkinson was director.
The 2012 Accession included additions to the Cyclotron and Physics Department series and two new series: Consulting and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Automatic timers.; Cyclotrons.; Nuclear physics.; Parkinson, William Charles, 1918-; Physics.; Swimming.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automatic timers.; Cyclotrons.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Historical Information
  Biographical/Historical Information is a slim series at the beginning of the collection which includes a vita and retirement biography.
  - Vita, etc. (Box 1)
- Cyclotron 1950-1983
  - 1950-1983
    Cyclotron, 1950-1983 (1.3 linear feet) includes material on the research projects and administration of the cyclotron laboratory, and reflect the growth of the laboratory and the various research projects, especially with the 83-inch cyclotron. The series includes correspondence with the Atomic Energy Commission (AEC), laboratory annual reports, progress reports, and proposals. The AEC correspondence reflects Parkinson's order which accounts for the overlap of dates. The "Equipment Disposal" folder includes a written "History of the Cyclotron Disposal" that describes the dismantling of the laboratory and dispersal of equipment following the 1977 decision to close the laboratory due to lack of funding. Also of interest to the researcher will be the folder entitled "Newspaper Clippings and Photographs." The materials capture some of the building activities and remodeling of the laboratory that took place in 1960 and 1961. This series is comprised of materials received in the first accession and is continued in the 2012 accession.
    - Atomic Energy Commission correspondence 1956-1976, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Cyclotron building committee 1952-1966 (Box 1)
    - Cyclotron building extension 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Cyclotron Laboratory Annual Reports 1968-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 83-inch cyclotron (Box 1)
    - Original proposal and final report 1958, 1963, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Progress reports October 1960-March 1964 (Box 1)
    - Shielding and radiation survey 1964, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Equipment disposal 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (includes "History of the Cyclotron Disposal")
    - 50-inch cyclotron (Box 1)
    - General 1966, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Proposals and contracts 1950-1963 (Box 1)
    - National Science Foundation proposal and correspondence 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Neutron Therapy proposal 1971-1975 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Progress reports 1950, 1952-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1960-1977
    Cyclotron, 1960-1977 (0.30 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, extends the series from the first accession. The new accession consists of correspondence, annual budgets, laboratory personnel records, and published materials related to the University of Michigan's 83-inch cyclotron.
    - Annual equipment budgets 1968-1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1975 (Box 3)
    - Cyclotron lectures undated (Box 3)
    - Design Study of Radio Frequency Systems for the University of Michigan 83-inch Cyclotron January 1961 (Box 3)
    - Funding correspondence 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Isochronous Cyclotrons, International Cyclotron Conference September 17-19, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Laboratory personnel 1960-1975, 6 folders (Box 4)
- Physics Department 1949-1995
  - 1964-1986
    Physics Department, 1964-1986 (0.4 linear feet) reflects Parkinson's participation in the physics department administration and professorial duties as well as cyclotron information. The eight folders entitled "Correspondence" include a file index for each year. Included in the "History of Physics" folder is a copy of the paper Parkinson wrote in 1986 regarding the history of nuclear physics at the University of Michigan. Like the Cyclotron series, this series is continued in the 2012 accession.
    - Correspondence 1969-1975, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - General correspondence 1964-1977 (Box 2)
    - History of Physics at Michigan: Nuclear Physics 1986 Paper (Box 2)
    - National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory (MSU) 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Proposals 1963 (Box 2)
    - Summer Symposium 1953-1973 (Box 2)
  - 1949-1995
    Physics Department, 1938-1997 (1.2 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, extends the series from the first accession. The new accession consists primarily of correspondence and teaching materials. Also included are records regarding Parkinson's sabbaticals and international work in China and the United Kingdom. Of particular interest is "Notes Concerning the Far Infra Red Vacuum Recording Spectrograph", a laboratory notebook written by Nelson Fuson, a physicist and conscientious objector during World War II.
    - Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge University Sabbatical 1949-1954 (Box 4)
    - Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge University Sabbatical Correspondence 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1945-1992, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Department correspondence 1957-1963, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Department materials 1978-1992, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Electromagnetism and Health talk October 22, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Electronic Circuits manuscript undated, 6 folders (Box 4)
      (Unfinished -- no Chapters 11; 14-21)
    - Foreign travel reports 1958-1973 (Box 4)
    - H. Richard Crane dinner remarks November 7-8, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Karl T. Hecht correspondence 1964 (Box 4)
    - Karl T. Hecht Symposium speech September 16, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Medical physics 1984-1988, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Notes Concerning the Far Infra Red Vacuum Recording Spectrograph by Nelson Fuson & general lab notes 1938 (Box 4)
    - Nuclear Colloquium schedules 1960-1973 (Box 4)
    - People to People Biophysics Delegation to the People's Republic of China 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - People to People Biophysics Delegation to the People's Republic of China journal November 9-30, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Personal and sabbatical correspondence 1966-1993, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Photographic negatives correspondence December 15-21, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Physics 126b course materials 1966 (Box 5)
    - Physics 166 course materials 1951-1958, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Physics 197 course materials 1958-1960, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Physics 455 course materials 1974-1980, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Stripping correspondence 1953-1963, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Professional Organizations 1958-1972
  Professional Organizations, 1958-1972 (0.4 linear feet) documents the organizational committees work in which Parkinson participated on a national level. These organizations include Argonne National Laboratory, Atomic Energy Commission, National Academy of Science, and the National Science Foundation. Correspondence between Parkinson and other members of these groups show the dynamics of these relationships.
  - Argonne National Laboratory Physics Review 1958-1961 (Box 2)
  - Argonne Universities Association 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Atomic Energy Commission Acceleration Panel 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Bonner Prize Committee 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Midwest Nuclear Group 1975-1982 (Box 2)
  - National Academy of Science Post-Doctoral Committee 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Advisory Panel and Site Committee 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation Physics Advisory Council 1966-1970 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Nuclear Data Committee 1972-1973 (Box 3)
- Swimming Judging and Timing System 1955-1978
  In the Swimming Judging and Timing System series, 1955-1978 (0.4 linear feet), information on Parkinson's invention can be found. Correspondence regarding the methods he used can be found here as well as responses from other companies and schools who tested out his system. The "Patent Information" folders include material on references to his system and correspondence regarding royalty problems. The original patent information can be found in the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics record group in the Bentley Library. In the "Correspondence" files, there are drawings of various components of the timing system with references to their operation. Photographs of the system are located in Visual Materials.
  - Correspondence 1955-1978, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings 1956-1990 (Box 3)
  - Patent information 1961-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
- University Committees
  Parkinson's involvement with University of Michigan committees is well-documented in the University Committees series, 1955-1987 (0.25 linear feet). Committees ranging from athletics to academic policies to research policies are covered. In the "Sigma Xi, Michigan Chapter" folder, handwritten introductions and speeches Parkinson made while serving as president can be found. Many of the committees are documented in other Bentley collections.
  - Academic Appeals Panel 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Administrative Board 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Biophysics Research Division Executive Committee 1978-1986 (Box 3)
  - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Campus committees 1955-1976 (Box 3)
  - Classified Research Review Panel 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Office of Research Administration Executive Committee 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Project MICHIGAN 1956-1958 (Box 3)
  - Rackham Divisional Board 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Residential College Board
    - Joint Board 1977-1980 (Box 3)
    - Search Committee 1977 (Box 3)
  - SACUA Research Policy 1963 (Box 3)
  - Sawyer Day 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Sesquicentennial Committee 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Sigma Xi, Michigan Chapter 1962-1965 (Box 3)
  - Technology Museum Project 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - University Stores Purchasing Problem 1980-1981 (Box 3)
- Consulting
  Consulting, 1946-1973 (0.15 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, consists of correspondence and contracts related to Parkinson's consulting work outside of the University.
  - Consulting 1951-1973, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Technical 1946-1962 (Box 3)
  - Union Carbide Nuclear Company, Oak Ridge, Tennessee 1954-1960 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials 1928-1974
  Visual Materials, 1928-1974 (0.75 linear feet) consists of lantern slides, negatives, prints, and slides related to the Cyclotron, Physics Department, and the swimming and judging system. This series contains both color and black and white images of the 29-inch, 42-inch, and 83-inch cyclotron, spanning from the original setting in Randall Lab, the 83-inch Cyclotron facility's construction, and experimentation through the mid-1970s. Also included are photographs, negatives, and slides of personnel such as H. Richard "Dick" Crane, David M. Dennison, William E. "Bill" Downer, and Joachim "Joe" Koenig.
  - Photographs
    - Cyclotron photographs 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Cyclotron with Andrew Poltorak, Gerd Muehllehner, and Parkinson 1971 (Box 5)
    - Cyclotron with staff photographs undated (Box 5)
    - Dennison photographs undated (Box 5)
    - Department of Physics and Cyclotron slides 1941, 1963-1973 (Box 5)
    - Department of Physics Summer Symposium photographs
      - 1928-1929 (Box 5)
      - 1932-1934 (Box 5)
      - 1937 (Box 5)
      - 1941 (Box 5)
    - Equipment prints: #A-5472 Project 2170-1-P August 1954 (Box 5)
    - Photographs undated (Box 5)
    - Staff photographs 1951-1974, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Swimming and judging system photographs undated (Box 5)
    - Cyclotron construction photographs 1960-1965, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Lantern Slides
    - #1, Schematic particular to U-M cyclotron undated (Box 6)
    - #11, Crane, H. Richard "Dick" experiments, high voltage accelerator undated (Box 6)
    - #24, Crane experiments, injector for the electron synchrotron undated (Box 6)
    - #27, Crane and race track synchrotron circa 1950 (Box 6)
    - #28, Crane with synchrotron circa 1952-1953 (Box 6)
    - #29, Crane experiments, injector for the electron synchrotron undated (Box 6)
    - #62, 29-inch cyclotron in Randall Lab circa 1950 (Box 6)
    - #63, 29-inch cyclotron in Randall Lab circa 1950 (Box 6)
    - #67, Unknown machinery in Randall Lab circa 1954 (Box 6)
    - #69, 29-inch cyclotron in basement of Randall Lab with extraction beam on circa 1950 (Box 6)
    - #71, Chamber with coils, extraction beam undated (Box 6)
    - #87, Schematic particular to U-M cyclotron undated (Box 6)
    - #88, Small 29-inch cyclotron in the basement of Randall Lab undated (Box 6)
    - #96, Cyclotron undated (Box 6)
    - #98, R.F. system undated (Box 6)
    - #103, 83-inch cyclotron control panel circa 1964 (Box 6)
    - #108, Parkinson, William with beam preparation magnet undated (Box 6)
    - #109, Analyzing magnets and externals of radio frequency undated (Box 6)
    - #112, Downer, William E. and Parkinson with scattering chamber undated (Box 6)
    - #114, Downer, with cyclotron undated (Box 6)
    - #116, Cyclotron scattering chamber and analyzing magnets undated (Box 6)
    - #123, Scattering chamber schematic undated (Box 6)
    - #126, Diagram of D.P. stripping reactions undated (Box 6)
    - #127, Diagram of D.P. stripping reactions undated (Box 6)
    - Unnumbered
      - 83-inch cyclotron diagram with proposed four magnets undated (Box 6)
      - Cyclotron undated, 2 slides (Box 6)
      - Downer undated (Box 6)
      - Equipment room/general assembly area for new cyclotron, North Campus undated, 2 slides (Box 6)
  - Negatives
    - Bardwick, John undated (Box 6)
    - Cyclotron personnel undated (Box 6)
    - Downer with 83-inch cyclotron under construction undated (Box 6)
    - Downer March 1971 (Box 6)
    - Koenig, Joachim "Joe" undated (Box 6)
    - Koenig, in 83-inch cyclotron control room undated (Box 6)
    - #A5475 42-inch equipment and time of flight August 1954 (Box 6)
    - #A6539 83-inch cyclotron construction July 1961 (Box 6)
    - #A6542 83-inch cyclotron components July 1961 (Box 6)
    - #2842
      - 83-inch cyclotron April 16, 1964 (Box 6)
      - 83-inch cyclotron April 20, 1966 (Box 6)
      - 83-inch cyclotron analyzing magnets June, 1968 (Box 6)
      - 83-inch cyclotron, conceptual drawing of four magnet cyclotron December 15, 1958 (Box 6)
      - Electronic mappers with Koenig, Doug Schlede, and Betty Stark May 26, 1958 (Box 6)
    - #4939
      - Cyclotron and staff March 5, 1965 (Box 6)
      - Cyclotron personnel November 21, 1969 (Box 6)
      - Downer experiment machinery May 10, 1967 (Box 6)
      - Maring 50-inch and 83-inch cyclotron steel March 18, 1963 (Box 6)
    - #10643
      - 83-inch cyclotron, neutron time of flight tunnel and equipment, PDP 15 Computer May 10, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Neutron time of flight tunnel and equipment February 27, 1974 (Box 6)
    - #101900 Dennison, David M. presentation images with correspondence from Niels Bohr and Erwin Schrodinger January 29, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Slides
    - #1, Cyclotron equipment to rotate samples undated (Box 6)
    - #2, Prince, Mel undated (Box 6)
    - #3, Cyclotron June, 1964 (Box 6)
    - #5, Analyzing magnets undated (Box 6)
    - #9, Cyclotron June, 1964 (Box 6)
    - #10, Cyclotron June, 1964 (Box 6)
    - #11, Cyclotron, Crane and Glover with synchrotron undated (Box 6)
    - #14, Cyclotron June, 1964 (Box 6)
    - #16, Cyclotron and staff June, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Randall, Harrison at 93 with 42-inch cyclotron 1963 (Box 6)
    - Unnumbered
      - 42-inch Neutron Time of Flight 1954 (Box 6)
      - Cyclotron undated, 3 slides (Box 6)
      - Lab technician in Randall Lab undated (Box 6)
      - Staff undated (Box 6)